Guide to the Edward Otho Cresap Ord Letters, 1854-1885
Department of Special Collections
Edward Otho Cresap Ord Letters,
1854-1885
Special Collections M210
Ord, Edward Otho Cresap, 1818-1883
.75 linear ft. (269 items)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Purchased from Walter R. Benjamin Autographs, 1970
BIOGRAPHY
1818 Born Maryland
1835-39 Cadet, Military Academy
1839, July 1 2nd Lt., 3rd Artillery
1839-42 Florida War against Seminole Indians
1841, July 1 1st Lt., 3rd Artillery
1842-44 Ft. Macon, North Carolina
1845-46 Coast Survey
1846 Recruiting Service
1846-47 Voyage to California
1847-48 Mexican War--serving in California
1847-50 Monterey, California
1850, Sept. 7 Capt., 3rd Artillery
1851-52 Ft. Independence, Massachusetts
1852-55 Coast Survey
1855 Benicia, California
1855 Yakima Expedition
1856 Benicia, California
1856 Rogue River Expedition; action of Mackanootney Villages and Chefeco Creek
1856-58 Benicia, California
1858 Ft. Miller, California; frontier duty
1858 Spokane Expedition; combat of Four Lakes and Spokane Plain, skirmish of Spokane River
1859 Ft. Monroe, Virginia (Artillery School for Practice)
1859 On Harper's Ferry Expedition to suppress John Brown's Raid
1859-60 Ft. Monroe, Virginia
1861 Ft. Vancouver Washington; frontier duty
186l Benicia, California and San Francisco
1851-62 In command of a brigade of the Army of the Potomac
1861, Sept. 14 Brig. General, U.S. Volunteers
1861, Nov. 21 Major, 4th Artillery
1861, Dec. 20 In command of engaged troops at Drainsville, Virginia
1861, Dec. Bvt. Lieut. Col. for gallant and meritorious service at Battle of Drainsville.
1862, May-June In command of division in the Department of the Rappahannock
1862, May 2 Major General, U.S. Volunteers
1862, June-Aug. In command of Corinth, Mississippi
1862, Aug.-Sept. In Major General Grant's operations in Mississippi, commanding left wing of army
1862, Sept. 19 Battle of Iuka; Bvt. Colonel for gallant and meritorious services
1862, Sept.-Oct. In command of the District of Jackson, Tennessee
1862, Oct. 5 Battle of the Hatchie, severely wounded while commanding
1862-63 Military Commission investigating Gen. Buell's Campaign in Kentucky and Tennessee
1863, June-Oct. In command of 13th Army Corps--engaged in Siege of Vicksburg, capture of Jackson
1864, Jan.-Feb. Commanded 13th Army Corps in the Department of the Gulf
1864, April-July Commanded troops in West Virginia
1864, July Commanded 8th Army Corps and all troops in Middle Department
1864, July-Sept. Commanded 18th Army Corps; in operations against Richmond; wounded in assault and capture of Ft. Harrison (Sept. 29)
1865, Jan.-Feb. Commanded Department of Virginia and North Carolina
1865, Feb.-June Commanded Department of Virginia; engaged Siege of Petersburg, pursuit of Rebel Army to capitulation of Lee at Appomattox
1865, March 13 Bvt. Brig. General for service at Battle of the Hatchie
1865, March 13 Bvt. Major General U.S.A. for services in assault on Ft. Harrison
1865-66 Commanded Department of the Ohio
1866-67 Commanded Department of the Arkansas
1866, Sept. 1 Mustered out of Volunteer Service
1867-68 Commanded: Fourth Military District (Arkansas and Mississippi)
1868-71 Commanded: Department of California
1871-75 Commanded: Department of the Platte
1875-80 Commanded: Department of Texas
1880, Dec. 6 Retired from active service
1881, Jan. 28 Major General
1883, July 22 Died at Havana Cuba
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The General Edward O. C. Ord Letters total approximately 260 letters, the first written in Oct. 5, 1854 (two days before he married) and extending through January 30, 1885. The early letters from Oct. 5, 1854 -April 2, 1855 were written from Los Angeles, from on board the schooner Golden Gate, in San Pedro, and other such places. Some of those following are addressed from the Rogue River, Oregon Territory, Fort Vancouver, Washington, San Francisco, Ft. Miller and camps in Yakima country.
While many letters contain purely personal matters, others contain much of historical interest. On Jan. 24, 1855, he speaks of camping at San Pedro and in the next few letters he talks of various surveys he participated in. When he gets to the Oregon Territory, he talks of Indians being taken to reservations and again of Indian troubles (there was much Indian fighting going on at the time.)
Several letters are incomplete and many are frayed or have minor breaks at the folds.
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, undated and 1854 -1856 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. ND.Cover addressed to Ord. Ord ANS on verso
    "Marcy read it and write."
  - 2. [1854, Oct. 5?]NP. Frag. ALS. Ord to [Mary] in pencil.
    Note signed L.O.M.: "A note just before his wedding day of Capt. E.O.C. Ord to Mary Mercer Thompson Oct. 1854. Mercer Thompson was then ill with typhoid fever."
  - 3. ND."On board the Josiah... [or Goliah]." "Halfway to Monterey." ALS. Ord to Molly.
    "I have come to the conclusion that this being away on the coast Survey don't pay." his company being the garrison at Benicia; steamer from the States headed for San Pedro.
  - 4. ND.NP. ALS.
  - 5. [1855], Jan. 11, 12.Los Angeles, ALS.
    Re: Marcy; Dominguez; Ord's brother; Monty on San Gabriel River; Mrs. Stearns; Mrs. Gates or Yates; and Mrs. Downey; Don Manuel; Doña Gracia; Mr. Brent; survey of the New Town; Mr. Greenwell to take Ord's place on Coast Survey; Santa Barbara Islands; "call on Capt. Sherman for more funds if your supply gives out."
  - 6. [1855], Jan. 24.San Pedro. ALS.
    Lynching of Mr. Brown; the Wheelers; Dominguez; Mrs. Ross; forty pounds a year salary; Capt. Shelby; Marcy laying off the new town; [R.A. Thompson]
  - 7. [1855], Jan. 28.Camp near San Pedro. ALS.
    Describes Santa Barbara Islands; Johnson's cove; "about 500 seals lay in a heap like pigs;" planted signal; red fish of 6 or 8 lbs.; Capt. shot quail: "As the song has it; let the kings who make the wars -do the fighting for themselves;" Col. Steptoe, Gov. of "Eutaw"; Shields' Army re-organization bill; the survey, Prof. Bache.
  - 8. 1855, Feb. 7.San Pedro. ALS.
    Gen. Wool, Col. Hays; surveying offers from Sepulvedas; Dominguez; Lugos; Wilson; B.D. Downey; Sandford; Brent; Pueblo; "new town of San Pedro; Col. Coffee; Gleason and Marcy; Las Bolsas.
  - 9. [1855, Feb. 10-17].NP. San Pedro. ALS.
    Murillo; sharks; ground owls; coyote; sand hill cranes, geese; kangaroo mice; armadillos; Mr. Stereford; Catalina Island; water fowl; Sugar cane; rancheros; Ramon Yorba; Abel Stearns; Col. Bell.
  - 10. [1855], [Feb. 17-19].New City [San Pedro]. ALS.
    Describes camp; Capt. Folsom; San Pedro property; Col. Coffee.
  - 11. [1855], Feb. 21.Camp near San Pedro. ALS.
    Dominguez's politics -Dr. Gwin; gold at Kern River mines; Mrs. Washington.
  - 12. [1855], Mar. 29.San Francisco. ALS.
    Family and friends; Mr. Lovel; quarters at Benicia.
  - 13. 1855, April 2.Los Angeles. ALS.
    Los Angeles people; to take trip to Tejon Reservation; to bring his parents to California.
  - 14. 1855, Sept. 4.San Francisco. ALS
  - 15. 1855, Oct. 24.Columbia River, O.T., 30 miles from Ft. Vancouver. ALS.
    Maj. Haller at the Dalles; to report to Maj. Rains at the Dalles; Indian outrages; describes coast and towns "and the villages are like those western vilages [sic] just started where the streets are full of stumps and girdled dead trees;" Astoria, Gen. Adair; Capt. Jones at Bencia.
  - 16. 1855, Oct. 26.Ft. Vancouver, Wn. Territory. ALS.
    Indian trouble exaggerated; Dr. Tripler.
  - 17. 1855, Nov. 4.Camp in Yakima Country. ALS.
    March after Indians.
  - 18. 1855, Nov. 12.Camp near Yakima Mission. ALS.
    Enemy have vanished; skirmishes with Indians; description of country; mission deserted; a command coming from Steilacoom.
  - 19. 1855, Nov. 21.Vancouver. ALS.
  - 20. 1855, Nov. (21-27).Vancouver, W.T. ALS.
    Desc. of Maj. Raines as a commander, $110 per month -and items, desc. Ft. Vancouver.
  - 21. 1855, Nov. 26.Dalles, Oregon Territory. ALS.
    Majs. Townsend and Cross; Capt. Cram; Cascades portage; descr. the Dalles quarters; pay account; Col. Coffee and Maj. Alvord.
  - 22. 1855, Dec. 4.Dalles. ALS.
    Col. Steptoe.
  - 23. 1855, Dec. 9.[Dalles]. NP. ALS.
    Duties; Col. Steptoe.
  - 24. 1855, Dec. 13.Fort Vancouver, W.T. ALS.
  - 25. [1855], Dec. 26-27.Ft. Steilacoom (probably Ft. Vancouver instead). ALS.
    Descr. of country and weather; Christmas; Maj. Townsend.
  - 26. 1856, Jan. 1-8.NP. ALS.
    Military dinner; descr. of Ft. [Vancouver]; social visits; descr. of officers and their wives; preferred charges against Maj. Raines; Capt. Eckerson; talks of northern and southern women; plans to write for the newspapers; Gen. Wool; Indians at Fort; gambling.
- Correspondence, 1856 Mar. 7 -1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1. 1856, Mar. 7.On board Steamer Columbia south of Crescent City. ALS.
    Isaac Stevens; Capt. Folsom; Col. Nauman; Indians turning themselves in.
  - 2. 1856, Mar. 13-15.Crescent City. ALS.
    To go into the interior; Crescent City; Dr. Gwin.
  - 3. 1856, Mar. 23-25.Camp at mouth of Rogue River. ALS.
    March from Crescent City; redwoods; sea coast; Col. Buchanan; Pistol River; Indians.
  - 4. 1856, Mar. 28.Camp at mouth of Rogue River.
    Indian Fight attacked while burning Indian "town" -that of the Macanootenays, "first time the Rogue River Indians have been well whipped and driven from their positions;" mismanagement of campaign.
  - 5. 1856, April 7.Camp at mouth of Rogue-River - near Fort Orford. ALS.
    Fight with Mackanootenays.
  - 6. 1856, April 9.Camp at mouth of Rogue River - Oregon Territory. ALS.
    Re: notes and sketches he hopes to publish; desc. of camp site; sea lions, seals and "porpuses"; remains of mining ventures; mud fort and inhabitants; story of Indian captivity.
  - 7. 1856, April 12-14.Port Orford, Oregon Territory. ALS.
    Col. Buchanan; Sgt. Nahs.
  - 7b. 1856, May 6.Big Bend Rogue River - Oregon Territory. ALS & typed transcript
    re: poison oak. Gen WF, escape from Indians, "Old John", "George", supply train saved.
  - 8. 1856, May7.Camp at the mouth of Rogue River, Oregon Territory. ALS.
    [Frag] another brush with Indians; Indians want to talk; Ord's newpapers articles.
  - 9. 1856, 9 May 9.Camp at Big Bend, Rogue River, Oregon Territory. ALS.
    Indians giving up, to be moved to reserve; Capt. Smith, Lupton's massacre of Indians; white and Indians "unworthy the interest government displays in them;" Augur and Bledsoe; descr. of Indians in camp.
  - 10. 1856, May 23.Fort Orford, 0. Territory. ALS.
    Chief "George" and band at mouth of Illinois; Capt. Smith; head dress.
  - 11. [1856], June 11.Camp on the road from Rogue River to Fort Orford. ALS.
    Rogue River war fast closing; "Old John".
  - 12. [1856?], June 19.Camp, Mouth of Rogue River, 0[regon] T[erritory]. ALS.
    To bring in 250 Indians to Fort Orford; re: Col. B[ell] and Gen. Wool; Braggs Battery.
  - 13. 1856, June 23.Fort Orford, O.T. ALS.
    Col. Buchanan; Lt. Crookes.
  - 14. 1857, Sept. 18.San Francisco. ALS.
    Won't have to go to Oregon.
  - 15. 1858, March 13.Benicia, Cal. ALS.
    Description of new post [Fort Miller].
  - 16. 1858, Mar. 19.Benicia, ALS.
    Moving to Fort Miller; fleas; shopping.
  - 17. 1858, Mar. 23.Ft. Miller, ALS.
    Trip and arrival; Lt. Kellogg; barren country; descr. of quarters.
  - 18. 1858, April 6.Fort Miller. ALS.
    Millerton; neglect in country Post Offices.
  - 19. 1858, April [12-13?].Fort Miller. ALS.
    Failure of Army bill; quarters; fashions; sketch and floor plan of quarters; birds and animals.
  - 20. 1858, April 30 -[May 1?].Fort Miller. Frag.
    Extract of orders to Lt. Kellogg and part of Kellogg's report.
  - 21. [1858, April -May?].[Fort Miller]. AL. Frag.
  - 22. 1858, July 4.Fort Vancouver, Washington Territory. ALS.
    Description of area; Major Wyse; Col. Steptoe; Col. Morris; approaching campaign; new rifled musket; Maj. Andrews.
  - 23. 1858, July 7.Fort Vancouver, W.T. AL. Frag.
    Headed for Walla Walla; Col. Wright; Indians; mentions Salt Lake expedition; Steven's desire for land equals the cause of the present war; cost of waging it; politicians, Army and Indians; Steven's politics; Indian agents -Nesmith of Ore. and Henly of California.
  - 24. 1858, July 8.Ft. Vancouver. ALS.
    Hopes his Co. will be sent to Old Point; Company rivalry; Lt. Chandler.
  - 25. 1858, July 11.Ft. Vancouver, W.T. ALS.
    Gwins have gone to France.
  - 26. 1858, July 26.Fort Walla Walla, Wash. Territory. ALS.
    Cols. Wright and Steptoe, Capt. Keyes, Maj. Grier; countryside and camp; missionaries.
  - 27. 1858, Aug. 2.[Ft. Walla Walla]. ALS.
    Miners going to Yakima and Frazer valleys.
  - 28. 1858, Aug. 6.Walla Walla. ALS.
    Applying for school of Practice.
  - 29. 1858, Aug. 6.Fort Walla Walla, Wash. Territory. ALS.
    Council of the Nez Perces and Wright treaty of alliance; the Nez Perces, miners; a priest to accompany the march.
  - 30. [1858, Aug. 6].Ft. Walla Walla. ALS. [Frag.?].
    To "Dr. Brother;" start for Snake River, Nez Perces and treaty; Frazer River mines and gold.
  - 31. 1858 Aug. 11.Camp 'hole in the bluff' Snake River. ALS.
    The march, theft of oxen; Lt. Davidson; camp; weather and country.
  - 32. 1858, Aug. 17-19.Camp on Snake River. ALS.
    Talking with Indians; sketch of area and descr. of camp.
  - 33. 1858, Aug. 23.Camp on South side of Snake River. ALS.
    Nez Perce victory; Maj. Garnett's success; Chief Moses.
  - 34. 1858, Sept. 1-3.Camp on the four lakes near Spokane River. ALS.
    Account of the battle and sketch or plan; march; Capt. Keyes.
  - 35. 1858, Sept. 15.Camp at Coeur d'Alene Mission on Coeur d'Alene River. ALS.
    Making peace; march and battle; Spokane River; Keyes; descr. of country; capture of horses, "Slaughter Horse Camp"; Coeur d'Alene Lake, Mission valley and priests.
  - 36. 1858, Sept. 24.Spokane Country - Washington Territory, camp on the Lhatta - north of Snake River. ALS.
    Coeur d'Alene area; Father [Foset?]; making treaties with Spokanes and punishing Palouses and Yakimas -Owhye in irons and Qualchin hung.
- Correspondence, 1859 -1863 Dec. 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1. 1859, Mar. 9.Washington, D.C. To Molly Ord. Old Point Comfort, [Va.].
    Personal and family, Gwins (of California).
  - 2. 1859, Oct. 2.Ft. Moultrie, Sullivans Island, [S. Carolina]. To Molly Ord. Old Point Comfort, Va.
    Carolinas, trip, gossip.
  - 3. [1859], Oct. 7."Court Room Ft. Moultrie, Charleston, S. Carolina." To [Molly]. N.P. AL.
    Personal, description of court and quarters. Lower left quarter torn away.
  - 4. 1859, Oct. 22-24.Washington, D.C. To Molly. [Old Point].
    Harper's Ferry, Capt. Garresche, Bennett, patent, Baltimore, possible troop movements.
  - 5. 1859, Dec. 2.Harper's Ferry. To Molly. Old Point, Va.
    Description of Harper's Ferry, Col. Lee (R.E.), Mr. Fry, Col. Barbour, "Old Man Brown is in eternity and there is no more need even to get up an excitement for fear of a rescue, his remains are now arriving and to enter the cars for the north." Includes also sales catalog entry in typed, xerox and manuscript form.
  - 6. 1859, Dec. 6.Harper's Ferry. To Molly. [Old Point?].
    Harper's Ferry, personal.
  - 7. 1861, Oct. 19."Steamer St. Louis off Acapulco, Mex." To Molly. San Francisco.
    Voyage from S.F., Gen. & Mrs. Halleck, Col. Naglee, Maj. Drum, personal.
  - 8. 1861, Oct. 25."Off Panama." To Molly. San Francisco.
    Dangerous voyage, personal.
  - 9. 1861, Nov. 11.Washington, D.C., H.Q. Army of the Potomac. To Molly. San Francisco.
    Recent affair Pickens on La Rosa Island, Capt. Vogdes and mule into enemy ranks, Washington. Part torn off bottom.
  - 10. 1861, Nov. 26.[Washington, D.C.?]. [To Molly]. [N.P.]
    Pleased with Brigade, Major in 4th Artillery, Gen. Early, "peace must be upon a union basis," horses, Mr. Seward, Gov. Pickens & Davis. Damaged fragment.
  - 11. 1861, Dec. 18."Camp near Chain Bridge, D.C." To Molly. San Francisco.
    Washington, wants to transfer to 3rd Artillery, Col. Merchant and Maj. Wyse, "I am pretty well satisfied that this r[ebel]lion will soon collapse and that unl[ess] a foreign war is begun"..."should a war with England occur," Mr. Chase, Post Master Gen'l. Blair, Mr. Seward, Mr. Sharpe, brother Placidus, West Virginia, Brigade, note to Bertie.
  - 12. 1861, Dec. 24.Camp Pierpont, Va. To Molly. San Francisco.
    Quote from "Twas the Night Before Christmas", Drainsville victory and battle, Gen. McCall, Christmas.
  - 13. ND [1861?].NP. To Mary M. Ord. San Francisco.
    President's levee, hero's popularity, brother Placidus, war and illness, "the basis of our government I fear has been all wrong --it is based upon the intelligence of the masses or the people and the virtue of the politicians --I think if it had been based upon the gullibility of the people and the vices of the politicians it would have been much wiser...," fragment beginning on page 3.
  - 14. 1862, Jan. 1.Camp Pierpont, Va. To Molly. NP.
    Present of sword from Brigade, Drainsville, Gen. Orders No. 63 by cmd. of McClellan, s____ Williams, thanks to Ord et al Dec. 28, 1861.
  - 15. 1862, Jan. 16."Camp Near Washington, D.C." To [Molly]. NP.
    Working for brevet for Drainsville, Stanton, Senators, newspaper publicity, "I do not know but think "Old Gwin" is out also -I should like to know where Mrs. G____ is if there is any treason in the family and somebody must be confined I think she is the most to be dreaded", letter to children.
  - 16. 1862, Jan. 27."Camp near Washington". To Molly. NP. AL.
    Personal. Fragment?
  - 17. 1862, Feb. 7-13.Camp Pierpont, Va. (near Washington). To Molly. San Francisco.
    McClellans, Mr. Holladay, personal.
  - 18. 1862, Mar. 16."Camp near Alexandria". To Molly. NP.
    Muddy tramp towards Manassas, Drainsville, Gen. McDougal, war.
  - 19. [1862?].NP. To Bertie, Lillie and Eddie. NP.
    Letter to older children.
  - 20. [1862], Mar. 19.Camp near Alexandria. To Molly. NP.
    "I have not gone at length into my reasons for espousing the cause of the union with all my heart because you might not feel entirely as I do...", President, McClellan, "Slavery is a great evil...," to attack enemy in a few days.
  - 21. [1862 Spring].NP. To Lucy. NP.
    "Papa is more than ever tired of the war..."
  - 22. 1862, April 22.Camp on the Orange and Alex. R Road. To Molly. NP.
    The southern women, "the war can not be carried on much longer, it is too suicidal...", staff, Mr. Seward, "our soldiers... behaving very badly at times".
  - 23. 1862, May 4.In camp near Fredricksburgh. To Molly. NP.
    Ord confirmed as Maj. Gen., slavery, personal. Fragment, part of bottom gone.
  - 24. 1862, May 18-22.Camp opposite Fredericksburgh. To Molly. NP.
    The first or "Ords" Division -1st (or McDowells) Army Corps, promotion for gallantry in action, farewell to brigade, news of Southern relatives, "we will soon start South again -maybe for a battle".
  - 25. [1862], June 22.San Francisco. Mrs. Ord to Gen. Ord. NP.
    News of promotion, "relative position of a marshall of France," children, "I would not advocate abolition sentiments they will surely do you no good", relatives. AL. not signed.
  - 26. 1862, June 23.Corinth, Mississippi. To Molly. NP.
    Enemy left fortifications, Western Virginia, Mississippians, Dept. of the Miss., McDowell's interference, new cmds post and 2 divisions, trip from W. Va.
  - 27. [1862 July?].Corinth, Miss. To Molly. NP.
    Personal, disaster of the Potomac Army, war, lost money, descr. country & people, illness, Confederates lack doctors, hoarding food, Richmond battle. Fragment: half of pages 1 & 2 gone.
  - 28. 1862, Aug. 2.Corinth, Miss. To Molly. NP. [California].
    Fremont, McDowell & Shields, "not to express anti-union sentiments even however much you sympathise with Virginia ... widows ... secessionists ...have all been dropped from the pension rolls," "Gen. Rosencranz [sic] (who will make his march yet if he tries)."
  - 29. [1862, Aug. 2].[Corinth]. To Bertie. NP.
    Advice, quarters -empty house, lack of food.
  - 30. 1862, Aug. 24.Corinth, Miss. To Molly. NP.
    Climate, death of Maj. Williams at Baton Rouge, death of Plummer, trip into Tennessee, rebels obstruct trains.
  - 31. [1862, Sept.?].NP. [Corinth, Miss?]. To "Mama" [Molly]. NP. [Calif.].
    Finances, costs, war, letter to children.
  - 32. 1862, Sept. 2-11.Corinth, Miss. To [Molly]. NP.
    Trip to Tuscumbia, Ala., negroes leaving the country, train wreck, "I had to take a bold stand directly in the face of the Secretary of War --to prevent my suffering what has happened to Gen'l. Stevens, Gen'l Kearney and others is being sacrificed to the stupidity and ambition of such a commander as McDowell ... you can have no idea of the utter incompetence of the two great Genls. McDowell and Pope whom Stanton placed in power". ANS of Placidus Ord, letter to children.
  - 32a. [1862], Oct. 5.Pocahontas, Miss. ALS.
  - 33. 1862, Nov. 7.Carlisle, Pa. To [Molly]. NP.
    Leg wound, plans, "The Secty Stanton and the abolitionists don't like me," Seward & Brown aides on leave.
  - 34. [1862, Nov. 2?].NP. To Bertie, Lilly, Eddie, Lucinda. NP.
    Has been in a dangerous battle "only got a little bullet into his leg", received note from Dr. Ord.
  - 35. 1862, Nov. 15-18.Carlisle, Pa. To Molly. NP [S.F.].
    Recovering, ride in country side, finances, "as I am not a favorite with the present Secty of War I shall probably be left a Major."
  - 36. 1862, Nov. 15-18.[Carlisle, Pa.]. To Children. [S.F.].
    Recovering from wound, written on: 11/13/62, Frank J. Braunhall to E.O.C. Ord. ALS, J.C. Buttre to engrave Ord's portrait for "Our Heroes," asks for biographical sketch.
  - 37. 1862 Dec. 4-6.Cincinnati, Ohio. To Molly. NP.
    Wound, personal, "our Military Commission on Gen. Buell's Campaign adjourns tomorrow for Nashville, Dec. 6 --Louisville, Ky., visits, flirting, note to children, Danas & Buells.
  - 38. 1862. Dec. 15.Nashville, Tenn. To [Molly]. NP.
    Recovering, investigating operations of Genl. Buells Army, old friends, Gen. Sheridan "the short Lieut.," Nashville, Wm. B. Lewis, met Gov. Johnston [sic] (Andrew Johnson).
  - 39. 1862, Dec. 24.Nashville, Tenn. To [Molly]. NP.
    Buell Commission, wound healing, biography in the American Encyclopedia, Military Album.
  - 40. 1863, Feb. 13.Cincinnati, Ohio. To Molly. NP.
    Family planning to come East, Gen. Wright. Fragile.
  - 41. 1863, Feb. 24.Cincinnati, Ohio. To Molly. NP.
    Instructions re: voyage East, commission.
  - 42. [1863?], Mar. 23.Louisville, Ky. To Sam [Holliday]. [Calif.].
    Power of attorney, politics, Grant, slavery.
  - 43. 1863, May 24.Mr. Willards, Old Point Comfort, Va. To Molly. NP.
    Gen. Dix, Old Point news, to command forces West Point, considered an opponent of the administration, "if it gets around that my wife talks in opposition to the Government... " "Grant so far has whipt the enemy and invested Vicksburg," wishes, life insurance, loyalty, Van Dorn not loyal to his wife.
  - 44. ND.NP. [Vicksburg?]. [To Molly]. NP.
    Battle or seige, 700 yards from enemy, Grant, McDowell "made a lodgement in the crater of the mines," terrible hill to storm, battle losses. Fragment pp. 5 & 6 only.
  - 45. 1863, June 27.NP. [Vicksburg?]. To [Molly]. NP.
    Assault on McPherson's front, heavy losses some by accident, "The artillery ammunition furnished our thirty powder parrotts is so bad the shells so rotten...they kill more of our own men than of the enemy."
  - 46. 1863, July 5.Vicksburg. To [Molly]. NP.
    "this place is taken."
  - 47. [1863?].NP. To children. NP. Personal.
  - 48. 1863, July 17.Jacson, Miss. To [Molly]. NP.